<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The description and use of the double horizontall dyall</title>
            <author>Oughtred, William, 1575-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1632</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08583</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18899C.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S3161</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33143089</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33143089</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28220</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08583)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28220)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1881:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The description and use of the double horizontall dyall</title>
                  <author>Oughtred, William, 1575-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M. Flesher,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M DC XXXII [1632]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication (from t.p.): To the most noble, and hopeful gentleman, Sr. William Hovvard Knight of the Bath, and sonne to the right honorable and illustrious lord, Thomas, Earle of Arundel and Surrey, Earle Marshal of England, &amp;c.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁸.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sundials --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:28220:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:28220:1"/>
            <p>THE DESCRIPTION AND VSE OF THE double Horizontall Dyall.</p>
            <p>TO THE MOST NOBLE, AND HOPEFVL GENTLE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MAN S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. WILLIAM HOVVARD KNIGHT OF THE BATH, AND SONNE TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE AND IL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LVSTRIOVS LORD, THOMAS EARLE OF ARVNDEL AND SVRREY, EARLE MARSHAL OF ENGLAND, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by M. FLESHER. MDCXXXII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:28220:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:28220:2"/>
            <head>The deſcription, and uſe of the double <hi>Horizontall diall.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THere are upon the Plate two ſeverall Dyals. That which is outermoſt, is an ordinary dyal, divided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to howers and quarters, &amp; every quarter into three parts which are five minutes apeece: ſo that the whole hower is underſtood to containe 60. minutes. And for this Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all the ſhadow of the upper oblique, or ſlanting edge of the ſtile, or cock, doth ſerve.</p>
            <p>The other dyal, which is within, is the <hi>projection of the upper Hemiſphaere, upon the plaine of the Horizon:</hi> the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon</hi> it ſelfe is underſtood to be the innermoſt circle of the limbe: and is divided on both ſides from the points of <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt</hi> into degrees, noted with 10.20.30. &amp;c. as farre as need requireth: And the center of the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is the <hi>Zenith,</hi> or <hi>Verticall point.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Within the <hi>Horizon</hi> the middle ſtraight line pointing <hi>North</hi> and <hi>South,</hi> upon which the ſtile ſtandeth is the <hi>Meridian,</hi> or twelve a clocke line: and the other ſhort arching lines on both ſides of it, are the <hi>hower lines,</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed accordingly by their figures: and are divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into quarters by the ſmaller lines drawen between them: euery quarter containing 15. minuts.</p>
            <p>The two arches which croſſe the hower lines, mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on both ſides in the points of interſection of the ſixe a clock lines with the horizon, are the two ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circles of the <hi>Ecliptick</hi> or annuall circle of the ſunne: the upper of which arches ſerueth for the <hi>Summer</hi> halfe yeare; and the lower for the winter halfe yeare: and are therefore diuided into 365. dayes: which are alſo
<pb facs="tcp:28220:3"/>diſtinguiſhed into twelue months with longer lines, hauing their names ſet downe: and into tenths and fifts with ſhorter lines: and the reſt of the dayes with pricks as may plainly be ſeene in the dyall.</p>
            <p>And this is for the ready finding out of the <hi>place of the Sunne</hi> every <hi>day:</hi> and alſo for the ſhewing of the <hi>Sunnes yearely motion</hi> becauſe by this motion the ſunne goeth round about the heavens in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe of a year, making the foure parts, or ſeaſons thereof, namely the <hi>Spring</hi> in that quarter of the <hi>Ecliptic</hi> which beginnes at the <hi>interſection on the Eaſt</hi> ſide of the dyall, &amp; is therfore called <hi>the Vernall interſection.</hi> Then <hi>the Summer</hi> in that quarter of the <hi>Ecliptic.</hi> which beginneth at the <hi>interſecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the Meridian</hi> in the higheſt point next the <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nith.</hi> After that <hi>Autumne</hi> in that quarter of the <hi>Ecliptic</hi> which beginneth at the <hi>interſection</hi> on <hi>the Weſt</hi> ſide of the dyall, and is therfore called the <hi>Autumnall interſecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> and laſtly the <hi>Winter</hi> in that quarter of the <hi>Ecleptic,</hi> which beginneth at the <hi>interſection with the Meridian</hi> in the loweſt point next the <hi>Horizon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But beſides this <hi>yearely motion, the Sunne</hi> hath a <hi>diur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall</hi> or <hi>dayly motion,</hi> whereby it maketh day and night, with all the diverſities and inaequalities thereof: which is expreſſed by thoſe other <hi>circles drawen croſſe the hower lines;</hi> the midlemoſt whereof, being groſſer then the reſt meeting with the <hi>Ecliptic</hi> in the points of the <hi>Vernall,</hi> and <hi>Autumnall interſections,</hi> is the <hi>Aequinoctiall:</hi> and the reſt on both ſides of it are called the parallels, <hi>or diurnall arches of the ſunne,</hi> the two outermoſt whereof are the <hi>Tropicks,</hi> becauſe in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſun hath his furtheſt <hi>digreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> or <hi>Declination</hi> from the <hi>Aequinoctiall,</hi> which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees 23. ½: and thence beginneth againe to returne to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb facs="tcp:28220:3"/>the <hi>Equinoctiall.</hi> The upper of the two <hi>Tropics</hi> in this our Northerne <hi>hemiſphere</hi> is <hi>the Tropic of Cancer</hi> and the ſunne being in it, is higheſt into the North, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the longeſt day of Summer: And the lower next the <hi>horizon</hi> is the <hi>Tropic</hi> of <hi>Capricorne;</hi> and the ſunne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in it is loweſt into the <hi>South,</hi> making the ſhorteſt day of winter.</p>
            <p>Betweene the two <hi>Tropics</hi> and the <hi>Equinoctiall,</hi> infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite ſuch <hi>parallel circles</hi> are underſtood to be contained: for the Sunne, in what point ſoeuer of the <hi>Ecliptic</hi> it is caryed, deſcribeth by his <hi>lation</hi> a circle parallel to the <hi>Equinoctiall:</hi> yet thoſe <hi>parallels</hi> which are in the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, though drawen but to every ſecond degree of <hi>declination,</hi> may be ſufficient to direct the eye in magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and tracing out through every day of the whole yeare in the <hi>Ecliptic,</hi> a proper circle which may be the diurnall <hi>arch of the ſunne</hi> for that day. For vpon the right eſtimation of that imaginary parallel doth the manyfold uſe of this inſtrument eſpecially rely: becauſe the true place of the ſunne all that day is in ſome part or point of that circle. Wherefore for the better conceiuing and bearing in mind thereof, every fift <hi>parallel</hi> is herein made a little groſſer then the reſt.</p>
            <p>For this inner dyall ſerueth the ſhadow of the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right edge of the ſtile; which I therefore call the <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right ſhadow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus by <hi>the eye and view onely to behold and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the courſe of the ſunne, throughout the whole yeare both for his annuall and diurnall motion,</hi> may be the firſt uſe of this inſtrument.</p>
            <div n="2" type="application">
               <head>II uſe. To finde the <hi>declination of the ſunne</hi> every day.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:28220:4"/>
               <p>Looke the day of the moneth propoſed in the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliptick,</hi> and marke how many degrees the prick ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that day, is diſtant from the <hi>Aequinoctiall,</hi> either on the Summer or winter ſide. <hi>viz.</hi> North or South.</p>
               <p>Example 1. What will the <hi>declination</hi> of the ſunne be upon the eleventh day of <hi>Auguſt?</hi> Looke the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> &amp; you ſhall find it in the ſixt cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle above the <hi>Aequinoctiall:</hi> Now becauſe each paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel ſtandeth (as hath bin ſaid before) for two degrees, the ſunne ſhall that day decline Northwards 12. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees.</p>
               <p>Example 2. What declination hath the Sun upon the 24. day of <hi>March?</hi> Looke the 24. day of <hi>March,</hi> and you ſhall find it betweene the ſecond &amp; third nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne parallels, as it were an halfe and one fift part of that diſtance from the ſecond: Reckon therefore 4. degrees for the two circles, and one degree for the halfe ſpace: So ſhall the Sunnes declination be five de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and about one fift part of a degree northward that ſame day.</p>
               <p>Example 3. What declination hath the Sun upon the 13. day of <hi>November?</hi> Look the 13. day of <hi>Novemb.</hi> and you ſhal finde it below the <hi>Aequinoctial</hi> ten paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lels, and about one quarter which is 20. degrees and an halfe ſouthward. So much is the declination. And according to theſe examples judge of all the reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>III. Vſe.</hi> To find the diurnall arch, or circle of the ſunnes courſe every day.</head>
               <p>The ſunne every day by his motion (as hath bin ſaid) deſcribeth a circle parallel to the <hi>Equinoctiall,</hi> which is either one of the circles in the dial, or ſome-where betweene two of them. Firſt therefore ſeek the day of
<pb facs="tcp:28220:4"/>the moneth; and if it fall upon one of thoſe parallels; that is the circle of the Sunnes courſe that ſame day: But if it fall betweene any two of the parallels, imagine in your in inde, and eſtimate with your eye, another pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel through that point between thoſe two parallels keeping ſtil the ſame diſtance from each of them</p>
               <p>As in the firſt of the three former examples, The circle of the Sunnes courſe upon the 11. of Auguſt, ſhall be the very ſixt circle above the <hi>Equinoctiall</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the center.</p>
               <p>In example 2. The circle of the <hi>ſunnes courſe</hi> upon the 24. of March ſhall be an imaginary circle between the lecond and third parallels, ſtill keeping an halfe of that ſpace, and one fift part more of the reſt, from the ſecond.</p>
               <p>In example 3. The <hi>circle of the Sunnes courſe</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the 13. of Novemb: ſhall be an imaginary circle betweene the tenth and eleventh parallels below the <hi>Equinoctiall,</hi> ſtill keeping one quarter of that ſpace fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the tenth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>IIII. Vſe.</hi> To find the riſing and ſetting of the ſunne every day.</head>
               <p>Seeke out (as was laſt ſhewed) the imaginary circle or parallel of the ſunnes courſe for that day, and marke the point where it meeteth with the horizon, both on the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt</hi> ſides, for that is the very point of the Sunnes riſing, and ſetting that ſame day, and the hower lines which are on both ſides or it, by propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning the diſtance reaſonably, according to 15. mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuts for the quarter of the hower, wil ſhew the hower of the Sunnes riſing on the <hi>Eaſt</hi> ſide, &amp; the Sunnes ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on the <hi>Weſt</hi> ſide.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:28220:5"/>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="application">
               <head>V. uſe. To know the reaſon and manner of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaſing</hi> and <hi>decreaſing</hi> of the <hi>dayes &amp; nights</hi> throughout the whole yeare:</head>
               <p>When the Sunne is in the <hi>Equinoctiall,</hi> it riſeth and ſetteth at 6. a clock, for in the inſtrument the interſecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Equinoctial,</hi> and the <hi>Ecliptic</hi> with the <hi>Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon</hi> is in the ſixe a clocke circle on both ſides. But if the ſunne be out of the <hi>Equinoctiall</hi> declining toward the <hi>North,</hi> the interſections of the parallel of the ſunne with the <hi>horizon</hi> is before ſixe in the morning, and after 6. in the evening: and the <hi>diurnal arch</hi> greater then 12. howers; and ſo much more great, the greater the nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne declination is. Againe, if the ſunne be declining toward the South, the interſections of the parallel of the Sunne, with the <hi>horizon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> is after ſixe in the morning and before ſixe in the evening: and the <hi>diurnal arch</hi> leſſer then 12. howers; and by ſo much leſſer, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſoutherne declination is.</p>
               <p>And in thoſe places of the <hi>Ecliptic</hi> in which the Sun moſt ſpeedily changeth his declination, the length alſo of the day is moſt altered: and where the <hi>Ecliptic</hi> goeth moſt parallel to the <hi>Equinoctial</hi> changing the declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but little altered. As for example, when the ſunne is neere unto the Aequinoctiall on both ſides, the dayes increaſe and alſo decreaſe ſuddainly and apace; becauſe in thoſe places the <hi>Ecliptic</hi> inclineth to the <hi>Equinocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> in a maner like a ſtreight line, making ſenſible decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Againe when the ſunne is neare his greateſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, as in the height of Summer, and the depth of winter, the dayes keepe for a good time, as it were, at one ſtay, becauſe in theſe places the <hi>Ectiptic</hi> is in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner parallell to the <hi>Equinoctiall,</hi> the length of the
<pb facs="tcp:28220:5"/>day alſo is but little ſcarce altering the declinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And becauſe in thoſe two times of the yeare, the Sunne ſtandeth as it were ſtill at one declination, they are called the <hi>ſummer ſolſtice,</hi> and <hi>winter ſolſtice.</hi> And in the meane ſpace the nearer every place is to the <hi>Equinoctial,</hi> the greater is the diverſity of dayes.</p>
               <p>Wherfore we may hereby plainly ſee that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon received opinion, that in every moneth the dayes doe aequally increaſe, is erroueous.</p>
               <p>Alſo we may ſee that in parallels aequally diſtant fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Aequinoctiall, the day on the one ſide is aequall to the night on the other ſide.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>VI. Vſe.</hi> To find how farre the ſunne riſeth, and ſetteth from the true Eaſt and weſt points, which is called the ſunnes. Amplitude ortive; and occaſive.</head>
               <p>Seeke out (as was ſhewed in III. uſe) the imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry circle, or parallel of the ſuns courſe, and the points of that circle in the <hi>horizon,</hi> on the Eaſt and Weſt ſides cutteth the degree of the <hi>Amplitude</hi> ortive, and occaſive.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>VII. Vſe.</hi> To finde the length of every day and night.</head>
               <p>Double the hower of the Sunnes ſetting, and you ſhall have the length of the day; and double the hower of the Sunnes riſing, and you ſhall have the length of the night.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>VIII. Vſe.</hi> To finde the true place of the ſunne upon the diall, that is, the point of the inſtrument which anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to the place of the ſunne in the heavens at any time. which is the very ground of all the queſtions following.</head>
               <p>If the dyall be fixed upon a poſt: Looke what a clocke it is by the outward dyall, that is, looke what
<pb facs="tcp:28220:6"/>hower and part of hower the ſhadow of the ſlanting edge of the ſtile ſheweth in the outward limbe. Then behold the ſhadow of the upright edge, and marke what point thereof is upon that very hower, and part in the inner dyall among the parallels, that point is the true place of the Sun at the ſame inſtant.</p>
               <p>If the dyall be not fixed, and you have a <hi>Meridian line</hi> noted in any window where the Sun ſhineth: place the <hi>Meridian</hi> of your dyall upon the <hi>Meridian</hi> line gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſo that the top of the ſtile may point into the North and ſo the diall is as it were fixed, wherefore by the former rule you may find the place of the ſunne upon it.</p>
               <p>If the dyall be not fixed, neither you have a <hi>Meridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an line</hi> but you know the true hower of the day exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: hold the dyal even and parallel to the <hi>horizon,</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it til the ſlanting edge of the ſtile caſt his ſhadow juſtly upon the time or hower given: for then the dyall is truly placed, as upon a poſt. Seek therfore what point of the upright ſhadow falleth upon that very hower, and there is the place of the Sunne.</p>
               <p>But if your dyall be looſe, and you know neither the Meridian nor the tyme of the day. Friſt, by the day of the month in the Ecliptick find the ſunnes parallel, or diurnall arch for that day, then holding the dyall leuell to the horizon, move it every way untill the ſlanting ſhadow of the ſtile in the outward limb, and the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right ſhadow in the ſunnes diurnall arch, both ſhew the very ſame hower and minut, for that very point of the ſunnes parallel, which the upright ſhadow cutteth, is the true place of the Sunne on the dyal at that preſent.</p>
               <p>But note that by reaſon of the thicknes of the ſtile,
<pb facs="tcp:28220:6"/>and the bluntneſſe of the angle of the upright edg, the Sunne cannot come unto that edge for ſome ſpace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and after noone. And ſo during the time that the ſunn ſhineth not on that upright edge, the place of the Sunne in the dyall cannot be found. Wherefore they that make this kind of double dyall, are to be careful to file the upright edge of the ſtile as thinne &amp; ſharpe as poſſible may be.</p>
               <p>That which hath heere bin taught concerning the finding out the ſunnes true place in the dyal, ought per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly to be underſtood, that it may be readily, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xterouſly practized, for upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the true performance ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of dependeth all that followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>IX. Vſe.</hi> To find the hower of the day.</head>
               <p>If the dyall be faſtened upon a poſt: the hower by the outward dyall, or limbe is knowne of every one: &amp; the upright ſhadow in the ſuns parallel, or diurnal arch wil alſo ſhew the very ſame hower.</p>
               <p>But if the dyall be looſe, either hold it or ſet it paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel to the horizo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with the ſtile pointing into the North and move it gently every way untill the hower ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in both dyals exactly agreeth, or which is all one, find out the true place of the ſunne upon the dyall, as was taught in the former queſtion, for that point a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the hower lines ſheweth the hower of the day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>X. Vſe.</hi> To find out the Meridian, and other points of the compaſſe.</head>
               <p>Firſt you muſt ſeeke the true hower of the day (by the laſt queſtion) for in that ſituation the Meridian of the dyall ſtandeth directly North and South: and the Eaſt pointeth into the Eaſt, and the weſt into the weſt, and the reſt of the points may be given by allowing
<pb facs="tcp:28220:7"/>degr: 11. ¼ unto every point of the compaſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>XI. Vſe.</hi> To find out the Azumith of the ſunne, that is the diſtance of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erticall circle, in which the ſunne is at that preſent, from the Meridian.</head>
               <p>Set your dyall upon any plaine or flat which is paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel to the horizon, with the Meridian pointing directly North and South, as was laſt ſhewed: then follow with your eye the upright ſhadow in a ſtreight line, till it cutteth the horizon: for the degre in which the point of interſection is, ſhall ſhew how farre the ſuns <hi>Azumith</hi> is diſtant from the Eaſt and weſt points, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement thereof unto 90. ſhall give the diſtance therof from the Meridian.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>XII Vſe.</hi> To find out the Declination of any Wall upon which the ſunne ſhineth, that it, how farre that wall ſwerveth from the North or South, either Eaſtward or Weſtward.</head>
               <p>Take a board having one ſtreight edg, &amp; a line ſtricke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicular upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it; apply the ſtreight edg unto the wal at what tyme the ſun ſhineth upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, holding the board parallel to the horizon: Set the dyal thereon, &amp; move it gently every way, untill the ſame hower and minute be ſhewed in both dyals: and ſo let it ſtand: then if the dyal have one of the ſides parallel to the Meridian, ſtrike a line along that ſide upon the board, croſſing the perpendicular, or elſe with a bodkin make a point upon the board, at each end of the Meridian, and tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away the inſtrument from the board, and the board from the wall, lay a ruler to thoſe two points, &amp; draw a line croſſing the perpendicular: for the angle which that line maketh with the perpendicular, is the angle of the declination of the wall. And if it be a right angle,
<pb facs="tcp:28220:7"/>the wall is exactly Eaſt or weſt: But if that line be pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel to the perpendicular, the wall is direct North or South without any declination at all,</p>
               <p>You may alſo find out the declination of a wall, if the dyall be fixed on a poſt not very farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that wal; in this maner. Your board being applyed to the wal, as was ſhewed, hang up a thred with a plummet, ſo that the ſhadow of the thread may upon the board croſſe the perpendicular line: make two pricks in the ſhadow &amp; runn inſtantly to the dyall and looke the horizontall diſtance of the ſunnes Azumith, or upright ſhadow from the Meridian. Then through the two pricks draw a line croſſing the perpendicular: and upon the point of the interſection, make a circle aequal to the horizon of your inſtrument, in which circle you ſhall from the line through the two pricks meaſure the horizontall diſtance of the upright ſhadow, or Azumith from the Meridian, that way toward which the Meridian is: draw a line out of the center, to the end of that arch meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: and the angle which this laſt line maketh with the perpendicular, ſhal be aequall to the declination of the wall.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>XIII. Vſe.</hi> How to place the dyall upon a poſt without any other direction but it ſelfe.</head>
               <p>Set the dyall upon the poſt, with the ſtile into the North, as nere as you can gueſſe: then moue it this way and that way, till the ſame hower and minute be ſhewed, both in the outward &amp; inward dyals, by the ſeveral ſhadowes, as hath bin already taught, for then the dyal ſtandeth in its trueſt ſituation; wherefore let it be nailed downe in that very place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>XIIII. Vſe.</hi> To find the height of the Sun at high noone every day.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:28220:8"/>
               <p>Seeke out the diurnal arch or parallel of the ſunnes courſe, for that day (by uſe III.) and with a paire of compaſſes ſetting one foot in the center, &amp; the other in the point of interſectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that parllel with the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian, apply that ſame diſtance, unto the ſamidiame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter divided, for that meaſure ſhall therein ſhew the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of the ſunnes altitude above the horizon that day at high noone.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>XV. Vſe.</hi> To find the height of the ſunne at any hower or time of the day.</head>
               <p>Seeke out the diurnall arch, or parallel of the ſunnes courſe for that day: and marke what point of it is in the very hower &amp; minute propoſed. And with a paire of compaſſes, ſetting one foot in the center, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in that point of the parallel, apply the ſame di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance unto the ſemidiameter divided: for that meaſure ſhall ſhew the degree of the ſunnes altitude above the horizon at that time.</p>
               <p>And by this meanes you may find the height of the ſunne above the horizon at every hower through out the whole yeare for the making of rings and cylinders and other inſtruments which are uſed to ſhew the hower of the day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>XVI. Vſe</hi> The height of the ſunne being given to finde out the hower, or what it is a clocke.</head>
               <p>This is the converſe of the former; ſeeke therefore in the ſemidiameter divided the height of the ſunne given. And with a payre of compaſſes ſetting one foot in the center and the other at that height, apply the ſame diſtance, unto the diurnall arch, or parallel of the ſunne for that day: for that point of the diurnall arch, upon which that ſame diſtance ſhall light, is the true place of
<pb facs="tcp:28220:8"/>the ſunne upon the dyal; and ſheweth among the how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er lines, the true time of the day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>XVII. Vſe.</hi> Conſiderations for the uſe of the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the night.</head>
               <p>In ſuch queſtions as concerne the night, or the time before ſunne riſing, and after ſunne ſetting, the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment repreſenteth the lower hemiſphere, wherin the ſoutherne pole is elevated. And therefore the parallels which are above the Aequinoctiall toward the center, ſhal be for the ſoutherne, or winter parallels: and thoſe beneath the Aequinoctiall, for the Northerne or Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer parallels; and the Eaſt ſhall be accounted for Weſt, and the weſt for Eaſt; altogether contrary to that which was before, when the inſtrument repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented the upper hemiſphaere.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>XVIII. Vſe.</hi> To find how many degrees the ſunne is under the horizon at any time of the night.</head>
               <p>Seeke the declination of the ſun for the day propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed (by uſe II.) And at the ſame declination on the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ſide imagine a parallel for the Sun that night: and marke what point of it is in the very hower &amp; minute propoſed: And with a paire of compaſſes, ſetting one foot in the center, and the other in that point of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel, apply that ſame diſtance unto the ſemidiameter divided: for that meaſure ſhall ſhew the degree of the ſunnes depreſſion below the horizon at that time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>XIX. Vſe.</hi> To find out the length of the Crepuſculum, or twylight, every day.</head>
               <p>Seeke the declination of the ſun for the day propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed (by uſe II.) And at the ſame declination on the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ſide imagine a parallel for the ſun that night. And with a payre of compaſſes ſetting one foot in the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb facs="tcp:28220:9"/>and the other at 72. degrees upon the ſemidiame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter divided, apply that ſame diſtance, unto the ſunnes nocturnall parallel: for that point of the parallel, upon which that ſame diſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhal light, ſheweth among the hower lines, the beginning of the twilight in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or the end of the twilight in the evening.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>XX. Vſe.</hi> If the day of the month be not knowne, to find it out by the dyall.</head>
               <p>For the working of this queſtion, eyther the dyall muſt be fixed rightly on a poſt, or elſe you muſt have a true Meridian line drawne in ſome window where the ſun ſhineth, wherefore ſuppoſing the dyall to be juſtly ſet eyther upon the poſt, or upon the Meridian, Looke what a clock is it by the outward dyal, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve what point of the upright ſhadow falleth upon the very ſame minute in the inner dyall, and through that ſame point imagine a parallel circle for the ſunnes courſe; that imaginary circle in the Ecliptic ſhall cut the day of the moneth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe Inſtrumentall dyalls are made in braſſe by</hi> Elias Allen <hi>dwelling over againſt</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Clements <hi>Church without Temple-barre.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:28220:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
